You’re being inarticulate … the proper way is to say ‘what’s good’” Now you may think that’s too hood, that’s not cool But I’m here to tell you that even our language has rules So when Mommy mocks me and says “ya’ll-be-madd-going-to-the-store” I say “Mommy, no, that sentence is not following the law Never does the word "madd" go before a present participle That’s simply the principle of this English” If I had the vocal capacity I would sing this from every mountaintop, From every suburbia, and every hood ‘Cause the only God of language is the one recorded in the Genesis Of this world saying “it is good" So I may not always come before you with excellency of speech But do not judge me by my language and assume That I’m too ignorant to teach ‘Cause I speak three tongues One for each: Home, school and friends I’m a tri-lingual orator Sometimes I’m consistent with my language now Then switch it up so I don’t bore later Sometimes I fight back two tongues While I use the other one in the classroom And when I mistakenly mix them up I feel crazy like … I’m cooking in the bathroom I know that I had to borrow your language because mines was stolen But you can’t expect me to speak your history wholly while mines is broken These words are spoken By someone who is simply fed up with the Eurocentric ideals of this season And the reason I speak a composite version of your language Is because mines was raped away along with my history I speak broken English so the profusing gashes can remind us That our current state is not a mystery I’m so tired of the negative images that are driving my people mad So unless you’ve seen it rob a bank stop calling my hair bad I’m so sick of this nonsensical racial disparity So don’t call it good unless your hair is known for donating to charity As much as has been raped away from our people How can you expect me to treat their imprint on your language As anything less than equal Let there be no confusion Let there be no hesitation This is not a promotion of ignorance This is a linguistic celebration That’s why I put "tri-lingual" on my last job application I can help to diversify your consumer market is all I wanted them to know And when they call me for the interview I’ll be more than happy to show that I can say: “What’s good” “Whatagwan” And of course …“Hello” Because I’m “articulate” Thank you. (Applause)
Estás siendo inarticulado ... la forma correcta es decir "Qué hay de bueno" Ahora puedes pensar que es demasiado barrio, que eso no está bien Estoy aquí para decirte que nuestro lenguaje tiene reglas Así que cuando mamá se burla de mí y dice: "te-enojarás-yendo-a-la-tienda" Digo: "Mami, no, esa frase no sigue la ley La palabra "Mad" nunca debe ir antes de un participio presente Es el principio de este Inglés" Si tuviera la capacidad vocal cantaría esto desde cada cima de montaña, De todos los suburbios, y cada barrio Porque el único Dios del lenguaje es el registrado en el Génesis De este mundo diciendo "es bueno" Así que no siempre puedo venir ante ti con excelencia de palabra Pero no me juzgues por mi lengua y asumas que soy muy ignorante para enseñar Porque yo hablo tres lenguas Una para cada uno: Hogar, escuela y amigos Soy una oradora trilingüe A veces soy coherente con mi lengua ahora Lo encenderé para no aburrir después A veces me peleo entre dos lenguas Mientras que uso la otra en mis clases Y cuando por error las mezclo Me siento loca como... estar cocinando en el baño Sabía que tenía que pedir prestado tu idioma porque los míos fueron robados Pero no puedes esperar que hable de toda tu historia mientras la mía está rota Estas palabras son habladas Por alguien que está simplemente harto de los ideales Eurocéntricos de esta temporada Y la razón por la que habla una versión compuesta de tu idioma Se debe a que los míos fueron secuestrados junto con mi historia Hablo inglés roto por lo que los cortes pueden recordarnos Que nuestro estado actual no es un misterio Estoy cansada de las imágenes negativas que están enloqueciendo a mi gente Así que a menos que me hayas visto robar un banco deja de llamar malo a mi pelo Estoy tan harta de esta disparidad racial sin sentido No lo llamen bueno a menos que tu pelo sea conocido por donar para caridad Por mucho que haya sido raptada lejos de nuestro pueblo ¿Cómo puedes esperar que trate su huella en tu idioma como nada menos que igual? Que no haya confusión Que no haya ninguna duda Esto no es una promoción de la ignorancia Esta es una celebración lingüística Por eso puse "trilingüe" en mi última solicitud de empleo Puedo ayudar a diversificar su mercado de consumo es todo lo que quería que supieran Y cuando me llamen a la entrevista Estaré más que feliz de mostrar que Puedo decir: "¿Qué hay de bueno?" "Qué pasa?" Y por supuesto ... "Hola" Porque soy "articulada" Gracias. (Aplausos)